<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type='main'>64</title>
				<author>B.P. Grenfell</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Transcribed from images of original letters</resp>
					<name>Sarah Tew</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Entity tagging</resp>
					<name>Sarah Tew</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>XML encoding</resp>
					<name>Transkribus</name>
					<name>Sarah Tew</name></respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>tranScriptorium</publisher>
				<distributor>The Center for the Tebtunis Papyri, The University of California, Berkeley</distributor>
				<authority>The Board of Trinity College Dublin, The University of Dublin</authority>
				<date when="2022-05-16">May 16, 2022</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Available for academic research purposes only.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<settlement>Dublin</settlement>
						<repository>Trinity College</repository>
						<idno type="TC">IE TCD MS 4323</idno>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc>
						<objectDesc>
							<p>Handwritten postcard. Address written on rector, message written on verso. Printed text and stamp in green ink across top: 'POST CARD' with the British royal coat of arms between 'POST' and 'CARD'. Below 'POST CARD' is printed 'The address to be written on this side.' in small caps. Printed half-penny stamp in upper right. Two Circular postmarks in black ink, one at the top of the page and cut off, one directly on the printed stamp. Postmark on printed stamp reads: OXFORD/6.30PM/OC. 5/02. '64' written in pencil below printed stamp. Appears as though it may be an overwrite, perhaps on top of an erased '74' but highly uncertain.</p>
							<p>Printed postcard heading at top reads:</p>
							<ab type="pchead">
								<lb/>POST CARD
								<lb/><hi rend='smallcaps'>THE ADDRESS TO BE WRITTEN ON THIS SIDE.</hi>
							</ab>
						</objectDesc>
					</physDesc>
				</msDesc>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This document was created as part of a final project [insert further info/link on edition] by Sarah Tew in fulfillment of a Laurea Magistrale in Digital Humanities and Digital Knowledge at the University of Bologna under the supervision of Dr. Giulio Iovine (sponsor) and Dr. Paola Italia (co-sponsor) and in affiliation with Dr. Todd Hickey, Director of the Center for Tebtunis Papyri at the University of California, Berkeley.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p>Text has been transcribed diplomatically without corrections, normalization, or standardization.</p>
				<punctuation marks="all"><p>All punction marks have been retained nd represented using the appropriate Unicode code character except for apostrophes and ampersands which have been escaped using &apos; and &amp;, respectively.</p></punctuation>
				<segmentation><p>The text has been segmented into lines according to line breaks in the original text automatically by Transkribus and line groupings based on groups identified automatically or manually declared by Sarah Tew in Transkribus. Page breaks have been manually edited by Sarah Tew after export from Transkribus.</p></segmentation>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl partial="true">
				<namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
					<tagUsage gi="persName"/>
					<tagUsage gi="placeName"/>
					<tagUsage gi="orgName"/>
					<tagUsage gi="rs"/>
					<tagUsage gi="hi"/>
					<tagUsage gi="add"/>
					<tagUsage gi="del"/>
				</namespace>
			</tagsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en-GB">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handNotes><handNote>Written in black ink by B.P. Grenfell.</handNote>
			</handNotes>
			<correspDesc>
				<correspAction type="sent">
					<persName>B.P. Grenfell</persName>
					<placeName>Oxford</placeName>
					<date when="1902-10-05"></date>
				</correspAction>
				<correspAction type="received">
					<persName>J.G. Smyly</persName>
				</correspAction>
			</correspDesc>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2022-06-06" who="STew"> Manually added TEI header to Transkribus tei.xml exported file.</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<pb n='1'/>
			<ab type="address">
				<lb/><persName ref='Q76338502' n='Smyly, J. Gilbart' key='Smyly'>J. G. Smyly Esq</persName>
				<lb/>4 Merrion Square
				<lb/><placeName ref='Q1761' n='Dublin' key='Dublin'>Dublin</placeName>
				<lb/><placeName ref='Q57695350' n='Ireland' key='Ireland'>Ireland</placeName>
			</ab>
			<pb n='2'/>
			<ab type="dateline">
				<lb/>Oct 4.
			</ab>
			<ab>
				<lb/>The long expected letter has come from the American, and
				<lb/>everything is finished at last. The book<ptr/> is promised by
				<lb/>the 16th. Here is another conundrum. An astrological
				<lb/>calendar (2nd cent. A.D.). The days are grouped together
				<lb/>in fives with with elaborate description of the presiding deity (magical),
				<lb/>signs, wonders, diseases etc belonging to the particular
				<lb/>period. The entry dealing with Pharmouthi 16-20th begins
				<lb/>Φαρμοῦθι ἀπὸ ιϛ ἕως κ . ὑδροχόῳ ὅ ἐστιν μ εἰς<ptr/>
				<lb/>Φαρμουθι ἀπὸ ιϛ ἕως κ. ὁ δὲ κραταιος αὐτοῦ ὄνομα αὐτῷ
				<lb/>ἐστιν Νεβυ , μηνύει λέγων etc. <hi rend='underline'>What</hi> was in Aquarius
				<lb/>during these 5 days? and what does <foreign xml:lang='grc'>μ</foreign> refer to? Another
				<lb/>entry is Παχὼν ἀπὸ ια ἕως ιε. ἰχθύων ὁ ἐστιν
				<lb/>(blank space), Παχὼν ἀπὸ ια ἕως ιε. ὅ εστιν δεύτερος θεὸς<ptr/>
				<lb/>τῶν ἰχθύων , ὄνομα αὐτῷ εστιν etc. The papyrus is
				<lb/>very carelessly written. <persName ref='Q2568204' n='Mahaffy, John Pentland' key='Mahaffy'>Mahaffy</persName> arrives tomorrow Yours <persName ref='Q822668' n='Grenfell, Bernard Pyne' key='Grenfell'>B.P.G.</persName></ab>
			
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
